Niko Tapio Partanen

Lattice laboratory CNRS & Ecole normale supérieure/PSL & Univ. Sorbonne nouvelle / USPC 1 rue Maurice Arnoux F-92120 Montrouge France

Phone: +358405068571

Email: nikotapiopartanen@gmail.com Blog: langdoc.github.io (multiple authors)

Born: December 23, 1986-Finland

Nationality: Finnish

Current position

Visiting researcher, Lattice laboratory (Apr 2017-present)

Areas of specialization

I study sociolinguistic variation in Permic languages, but as a continuous side-project I investigate the applicability of computational methods to documentary linguistics data. I'm also studying topics related to language shift and language revitalization.

Keywords: Sociolinguistics, endangered languages, documentary linguistics, Natural Language Processing, corpus linguistics, Permic languages, research methodology

Positions held

2017-2019	Co-applicant in project Language Documentation meets Language Technology: The Next
	Step in the Description of Komi, funded by Kone Foundation
2015-2017	Software developer, INEL / Hamburger Zentrum für Sprachkorpora
2014-2015	PhD student in project Izhva Komi Language Documentation, funded by Kone
	Foundation. Freiburg Research Group in Saami Studies
2013	PI in project Down River Vashka, Komi (Udora dialect), funded by Kone Foundation and
	MinorEuRus
2012-2013	Research assistant, University of Helsinki

Education

MA in Finno-Ugric linguistics, University of Helsinki
BA in Finno-Ugric linguistics, University of Helsinki

fall 2011 north2north program exchange student, Syktyvkar State University

Grants, honors & awards

VIETS Master Thesis Prize, Finnish Association for Russian and Eastern European Studies

Publications and Presentations

PRESENTATIONS

2014

2017

2016

2016

2015

Niko Partanen: Issues with archiving linguistic data. Perspectives from work on Permic languages. Travaux de terrains anthropologiques et linguistiques : expériences et difficultés. 20, May, INALCO, Paris, France

Ciprian Gerstenberger, Niko Partanen & Michael Rießler: Instant annotations in ELAN corpora of spoken and written Komi-Zyrian, an endangered language of the Barents Sea region (Russia). ComputEL-2 (2nd Workshop on Computational Methods for Endangered Languages). 6-7 March, 2017, Honolulu, Hawaii

Niko Partanen: Challenges in OCR today. Report on experiences from INEL. Conference: Electronic Writing of RF Peoples: History, Issues, and Perspectives. 17 March, 2017, Syktyvkar

Niko Partanen: Russian influence across Komi registers. Colloquium "From Language Mixing to Fused Lects", Freiburg Institute for Advanced Studies, Albert-Ludwigs-Universität Freiburg, 25.–27. January, 2017, Freiburg

Daniel Jettka, Timm Lehmberg & Niko Partanen: Digital workflows. INEL workshop. 03. November, 2016. INEL / Hamburger Zentrum für Sprachkorpora, Hamburg.

Niko Partanen: Russian influence on Iźva Komi sibilant articulation. SLE conference, 25. August, 2016, Naples, Italy

Hanna Thiele, Niko Partanen ở Michael Rießler: Exploring constituent order variation in selected languages of the Barents Sea area. Transalpine Typology Meeting, 8−9 October, 2015, Lyon, France

Rogier Blokland, Michael Rießler, Niko Partanen & Joshua Wilbur: A critical evaluation of past, current and future approaches in Uralic language documentation. XII International Congress for Finno-Ugric Studies, 17–20 August, 2015, Oulu, Finland

- Partanen, Niko & Saarikivi, Janne: Linguistic variation in the Karelian communities. XII International Congress for Finno-Ugric Studies, 17–20 August, 2015, Oulu, Finland
- Rogier Blokland, Ciprian Gerstenberger, Marina Fedina, Niko Partanen, Michael Rießler, and Joshua Wilbur: Language documentation meets language technology. First International Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Uralic Languages. 16th January, 2015, Tromsø, Norway
- Saarikivi, Janne & Partanen, Niko: Rapid extinction or relative revitalization? Karelian and Komi language communities in comparison. International Conference on Minority Languages XIV, 11–14 September 2013, Graz, Austria
- Partanen, Niko (2012), Poster presentation: Language shift in Komi, Sociolinguistics Symposium 19, Berlin

JOURNAL ARTICLES AND FINAL PAPERS

- Ciprian Gerstenberger, Niko Partanen, Michael Rießler & Joshua Wilbur: Utilizing language technology in the documentation of endangered Uralic languages. Northern European Journal of Language Technology, 4, 29-47
- Partanen, Niko & Saarikivi, Janne (2016), Fragmentation of Karelian language and its community: growing variation at the threshold of the language shift. In: Toivanen, Reetta & Saarikivi, Janne (eds.), New and Old Language Diversities, Multilingual Matters
- Rogier Blokland, Michael Rießler, Niko Partanen, Marina Fedina & Andrei Chemyshev: Ispoľzovanie cifrovyx korpusov i komp'juternyx programm v dialektologičeskix issledovanijax: teoria i praktika. In: Khisamitdinova, F.G (ed). Räsäj xaliqtary teldäre dialektologijahynyn könüδäk mäśäläläre. XIV Bötä Räsäj fänni konferencija materialdary (Öfö, 20-22 nojabr', 2014 j.). Aktuaľnye problemy dialektologii jazykov narodov Rossii: Materialy XIV Vserossijskoj naučnoj konferencii (Ufa, 20-22 nojabrja 2014 g.). Ufa: IIJaL UNC RAN. 252–255.
- Partanen, Niko (2013), Kahden suomalais-ugrilaisen yhteisön kielenvaihdon vertailevaa tarkastelua: Tuuksa Karjalassa ja Koigort Komissa (Comparative examination of the language shift in two Uralic speech communities: Tuuksa in Karelia and Koigort in Komi), Unpublished Master Thesis, University of Helsinki
- Partanen, Niko (2013), Kielenvaihdon tarkastelua Vuokkiniemellä ja Viteleellä: Vuosien 2004 ja 2010 kenttätyöaineistojen analyysi (Observating the language shift in Vuokkiniemi and Vitele: analysis of the fieldwork materials from 2004 and 2010), *Unpublished Bachelor Thesis, University of Helsinki*

Воокѕ

forthcomin

Partanen, Niko & Saarikivi, Janne (eds.) (2017), Materiaaleja karjalan kielen nykytilasta (Materials on the current state of the Karelian language)

TEACHING

2017 Using ELA

Using ELAN to create and analyse spoken corpus, June 1–8. (Syktyvkar State University)

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Finnish: native

Komi-Zyrian: very good English: very good Italian: good Russian: good

Udmurt: conversational

Komi-Permyak: conversational

Swedish: conversational German: conversational French: actively learning

COMPUTER SKILLS

Good knowledge: R, GiellaTekno infrastructure, LaTeX, XML, GIS tools, OCR tools **Learning / actively using**: Python, audio processing methods, speech recognition

RECENT FIELDWORK EXPERIENCE WITH PERMIC LANGUAGES

Naryan-Mar, Nenetskiy Autonomous Okrug, two weeks Funded by Kone Foundation Izhemsky rayon, Komi Republic, two weeks Funded by Kone Foundation Udorsky rayon, Komi Republic, a month Funded by Kone Foundation and MinorEuRus	2016 2015 2015	Kola Peninsula, Murmanskiy Oblast, two weeks Funded by Kone Foundation Different regions in Udmurtia, ten days No external funding Izhemsky rayon, Komi Republic, five days Funded by Развития фундаментальных лингвистических исследований
Udorsky rayon, Komi Republic, a month Funded by Kone Foundation and MinorEuRus		Naryan-Mar, Nenetskiy Autonomous Okrug, two weeks Funded by Kone Foundation
Koygorodsky rayon, Komi Republic, two weeks Funded by MinorEuRus		, ,